<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.1">
  <title>Branding Horizon</title>
  <para>As of the Liberty release, Horizon has begun to conform more strictly to
            Bootstrap standards in an effort to embrace more responsive web design as well
            as alleviate the future need to re-brand new functionality for every release.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Supported Components</title>
    <para>The following components, organized by release, are the only ones that make
                full use of the Bootstrap theme architecture.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>8.0.0 (Liberty)</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <xref linkend="top-navbar"/>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <xref linkend="side-nav"/>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <xref linkend="pie-charts"/>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>9.0.0 (Mitaka)</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <xref linkend="tables"/>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <xref linkend="bar-charts"/>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <xref linkend="login"/>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <xref linkend="tabs"/>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <xref linkend="alerts"/>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <xref linkend="checkboxes"/>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Step 1</title>
    <para>The first step needed to create a custom branded theme for Horizon is to create
                a custom Bootstrap theme.  There are several tools to aid in this. Some of the
                more useful ones include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <link xlink:href="http://bootswatchr.com/create#!">Bootswatchr</link>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <link xlink:href="http://paintstrap.com">Paintstrap</link>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <link xlink:href="http://getbootstrap.com/customize/">Bootstrap</link>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <note>
      <para>Bootstrap uses LESS by default, but we use SCSS.  All of the above
                    tools will provide the <literal>variables.less</literal> file, which will need to be
                    converted to <literal>_variables.scss</literal></para>
    </note>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="top-navbar">
    <title>Top Navbar</title>
    <para>The top navbar in Horizon now uses a native Bootstrap <literal>navbar</literal>.  There are a
                number of variables that can be used to customize this element.  Please see the
                <emphasis role="bold">Navbar</emphasis> section of your variables file for specifics on what can be set: any
                variables that use <literal>navbar-default</literal>.</para>
    <para>It is important to also note that the navbar now uses native Bootstrap
                dropdowns, which are customizable with variables.  Please see the <emphasis role="bold">Dropdowns</emphasis>
                section of your variables file.</para>
    <para>The top navbar is now responsive on smaller screens.  When the window size hits
                your <literal>$screen-sm</literal> value, the topbar will compress into a design that is
                better suited for small screens.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="side-nav">
    <title>Side Nav</title>
    <para>The side navigation component has been refactored to use the native Stacked
                Pills element from Bootstrap.  See <emphasis role="bold">Pills</emphasis> section of your variables file
                for specific variables to customize.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Charts</title>
    <section xml:id="pie-charts">
      <title>Pie Charts</title>
      <para>Pie Charts are SVG elements.  SVG elements allow CSS customizations for
                    only a basic element’s look and feel (i.e. colors, size).</para>
      <para>Since there is no native element in Bootstrap specifically for pie charts,
                    the look and feel of the charts are inheriting from other elements of the
                    theme. Please see <literal>_pie_charts.scss</literal> for specifics.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="bar-charts">
      <title>Bar Charts</title>
      <para>Bar Charts can be either a Bootstrap Progress Bar or an SVG element. Either
                    implementation will use the Bootstrap Progress Bar styles.</para>
      <para>The SVG implementation will not make use of the customized Progress Bar
                    height though, so it is recommended that Bootstrap Progress Bars are used
                    whenever possible.</para>
      <para>Please see <literal>_bar_charts.scss</literal> for specifics on what can be customized for
                    SVGs.  See the <emphasis role="bold">Progress bars</emphasis> section of your variables file for specific
                    variables to customize.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="tables">
    <title>Tables</title>
    <para>The standard Django tables now make use of the native Bootstrap table markup.
                See <emphasis role="bold">Tables</emphasis> section of your variables file for variables to customize.</para>
    <para>The standard Bootstrap tables will be borderless by default.  If you wish to
                add a border, like the <literal>default</literal> theme, see
                <literal>openstack_dashboard/themes/default/horizon/components/_tables.scss</literal></para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="login">
    <title>Login</title>
    <section>
      <title>Login Splash Page</title>
      <para>The login splash page now uses a standard Bootstrap panel in its
                    implementation. See the <emphasis role="bold">Panels</emphasis> section in your variables file to variables
                    to easily customize.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Modal Login</title>
      <para>The modal login experience, as used when switching regions, uses a standard
                    Bootstrap dialog.  See the <emphasis role="bold">Modals</emphasis> section of your variables file for
                    specific variables to customize.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="tabs">
    <title>Tabs</title>
    <para>The standard tabs make use of the native Bootstrap tab markup.</para>
    <para>See <emphasis role="bold">Tabs</emphasis> section of your variables file for variables to customize.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="alerts">
    <title>Alerts</title>
    <para>Alerts use the basic Bootstrap brand colors.  See <emphasis role="bold">Colors</emphasis> section of your
                variables file for specifics.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="checkboxes">
    <title>Checkboxes</title>
    <para>Horizon uses icon fonts to represent checkboxes.  In order to customize
                this, you simply need to override the standard scss.  For an example of
                this, see themes/material/static/horizon/components/_checkboxes.scss</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Bootswatch and Material Design</title>
    <para><link xlink:href="http://bootswatch.com">Bootswatch</link> is a collection of free themes for Bootstrap and is now
                available for use in Horizon.</para>
    <para>In order to showcase what can be done to enhance an existing Bootstrap theme,
                Horizon now includes a secondary theme, roughly based on <link xlink:href="https://www.google.com/design/spec/material-design/introduction.html">Google’s Material
                    Design</link> called <literal>material</literal>.  Bootswatch’s <emphasis role="bold">Paper</emphasis> is a simple Bootstrap
                implementation of Material Design and is used by <literal>material</literal>.</para>
    <para>Bootswatch provides a number of other themes, that once Horizon is fully theme
                compliant, will allow easy toggling and customizations for darker or
                accessibility driven experiences.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Development Tips</title>
    <para>When developing a new theme for Horizon, it is required that the dynamically
                generated <literal>static</literal> directory be cleared after each change and the server
                restarted.  This is not always ideal.  If you wish to develop and not have
                to restart the server each time, it is recommended that you configure your
                development environment to not run in OFFLINE mode.  Simply verify the
                following settings in your local_settings.py:</para>
    <screen>COMPRESS_OFFLINE = False
COMPRESS_ENABLED = False</screen>
  </section>
</section>
