<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.1">
  <title>Create and manage networks</title>
  <para>The OpenStack Networking service provides a scalable system for managing
            the network connectivity within an OpenStack cloud deployment. It can
            easily and quickly react to changing network needs (for example,
            creating and assigning new IP addresses).</para>
  <para>Networking in OpenStack is complex. This section provides the basic
            instructions for creating a network and a router. For detailed
            information about managing networks, refer to the <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/neutron/latest/admin/">OpenStack Networking Guide</link>.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Create a network</title>
    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>Log in to the dashboard.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>Select the appropriate project from the drop down menu at the top left.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>On the <guilabel>Project</guilabel> tab, open the <guilabel>Network</guilabel> tab and
                        click <guilabel>Networks</guilabel> category.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>Click <guilabel>Create Network</guilabel>.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>In the <guilabel>Create Network</guilabel> dialog box, specify the following values.</para>
        <para><guilabel>Network</guilabel> tab</para>
        <para><guilabel>Network Name</guilabel>: Specify a name to identify the network.</para>
        <para><guilabel>Shared</guilabel>: Share the network with other projects. Non admin users
                        are not allowed to set shared option.</para>
        <para><guilabel>Admin State</guilabel>: The state to start the network in.</para>
        <para><guilabel>Create Subnet</guilabel>: Select this check box to create a subnet</para>
        <para>You do not have to specify a subnet when you create a network, but if
                        you do not specify a subnet, the network can not be attached to an instance.</para>
        <para><guilabel>Subnet</guilabel> tab</para>
        <para><guilabel>Subnet Name</guilabel>: Specify a name for the subnet.</para>
        <para><guilabel>Network Address</guilabel>: Specify the IP address for the subnet.</para>
        <para><guilabel>IP Version</guilabel>: Select IPv4 or IPv6.</para>
        <para><guilabel>Gateway IP</guilabel>: Specify an IP address for a specific gateway. This
                        parameter is optional.</para>
        <para><guilabel>Disable Gateway</guilabel>: Select this check box to disable a gateway IP
                        address.</para>
        <para><guilabel>Subnet Details</guilabel> tab</para>
        <para><guilabel>Enable DHCP</guilabel>: Select this check box to enable DHCP.</para>
        <para><guilabel>Allocation Pools</guilabel>: Specify IP address pools.</para>
        <para><guilabel>DNS Name Servers</guilabel>: Specify a name for the DNS server.</para>
        <para><guilabel>Host Routes</guilabel>: Specify the IP address of host routes.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>Click <guilabel>Create</guilabel>.</para>
        <para>The dashboard shows the network on the <guilabel>Networks</guilabel> tab.</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Create a router</title>
    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>Log in to the dashboard.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>Select the appropriate project from the drop down menu at the top left.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>On the <guilabel>Project</guilabel> tab, open the <guilabel>Network</guilabel> tab and
                        click <guilabel>Routers</guilabel> category.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>Click <guilabel>Create Router</guilabel>.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>In the <guilabel>Create Router</guilabel> dialog box, specify a name for the router
                        and <guilabel>External Network</guilabel>, and click <guilabel>Create Router</guilabel>.</para>
        <para>The new router is now displayed in the <guilabel>Routers</guilabel> tab.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>To connect a private network to the newly created router, perform the
                        following steps:</para>
        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>On the <guilabel>Routers</guilabel> tab, click the name of the router.</para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>On the <guilabel>Router Details</guilabel> page, click the <guilabel>Interfaces</guilabel>
                                tab, then click <guilabel>Add Interface</guilabel>.</para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>In the <guilabel>Add Interface</guilabel> dialog box, select a <guilabel>Subnet</guilabel>.</para>
            <para>Optionally, in the <guilabel>Add Interface</guilabel> dialog box, set an
                                <guilabel>IP Address</guilabel> for the router interface for the selected subnet.</para>
            <para>If you choose not to set the <guilabel>IP Address</guilabel> value, then by
                                default OpenStack Networking uses the first host IP address in the
                                subnet.</para>
            <para>The <guilabel>Router Name</guilabel> and <guilabel>Router ID</guilabel> fields are
                                automatically updated.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>Click <guilabel>Add Interface</guilabel>.</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
    <para>You have successfully created the router. You can view the new topology
                from the <guilabel>Network Topology</guilabel> tab.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Create a port</title>
    <warning>
      <para>Creating and managing ports requires administrator privileges.
                    Contact an administrator before adding or changing ports.</para>
    </warning>
    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>Log in to the dashboard.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>Select the appropriate project from the drop-down menu at the top left.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>On the <guilabel>Admin</guilabel> tab, click <guilabel>Networks</guilabel> category.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>Click on the <guilabel>Network Name</guilabel> of the network in which the port
                        has to be created.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>In the <guilabel>Create Port</guilabel> dialog box, specify the following values.</para>
        <para><guilabel>Name</guilabel>: Specify name to identify the port.</para>
        <para><guilabel>Device ID</guilabel>: Device ID attached to the port.</para>
        <para><guilabel>Device Owner</guilabel>: Device owner attached to the port.</para>
        <para><guilabel>Binding Host</guilabel>: The ID of the host where the port is allocated.</para>
        <para><guilabel>Binding VNIC Type</guilabel>: Select the VNIC type that is bound to the
                        neutron port.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>Click <guilabel>Create Port</guilabel>.</para>
        <para>The new port is now displayed in the <guilabel>Ports</guilabel> list.</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>
</section>
